Today's דף daf *Daf* is י"א *Yud Alef*. We pick up at
the bottom of י' עמוד ב' *Yud Amud Bet*. We are in
the middle of a story about אבשלום Avshalom *Avshalom* within the larger
context of the מידה כנגד מידה middah k'neged middah. *Midah Keneged Midah*
that started with סוטה Sotah *Sotah* and her punishments
and now assuming she was guilty. Anyway, now we're about אבשלום Avshalom
*Avshalom*, אבשלום Avshalom *Avshalom*, excuse me, ultimately his hair was the most
beautiful, almost divine thing about him and ultimately it was taken from
him at the end and here actually it was his downfall. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, where were we? תנו רבנן
*Tanu Rabbanan*, the first, the widest line. אבשלום Avshalom. נתגאה בשערו *Avshalom
Nitga'ah Besearo*. Okay, תנו רבנן אבשלום Avshalom בשערו מרד *Tanu Rabbanan Avshalom
Besearo Marad*, he rebelled with his hair. שנאמר shene'emar, וכאבשלום לא היה
איש יפה וגו' ובגלחו את ראשו והיה מקץ ימים לימים אשר יגלח
כי כבד עליו וגילחו ושקל את שער ראשו *Shenemar Vekha'avshalom Lo Hayah
Ish Yafeh etc. Uvegalcho Et Rosho Vehayah Miketz Yamim Leyamim Asher Yegaleach
Ki Kaved Alav Vegilcho Veshekal Et Sear Rosho*, so he would whenever
he had a major shaving because he had so much hair and
then he would weigh it. מאתים שקלים באבן המלך *Mataiyim Shekalim Be'even
Hamelech*. Anyway, and then the end of that story is that, you
know, is that he used that to be away from the king
and to gather people around him and ultimately to lead, you know,
to be to have this insurrection. So it's, you know, so the
question is both it provided the pretext and also presumably because it
was such a matter of pride, although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't
say that explicitly, you know, filled him with that sense that he
could be that he was deserving to be king. רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
of course reminds us, if you look at רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*, רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says מקץ ימים לימים משנה Mishna לשנה שנזיר עולם היה
ומגלח אחת לשנים עשר חודש *Miketz Yamim Leyamim Mishanah Leshanah Shenazir Olam
Hayah Umegaleach Achat Lesheneim Asar Chodesh*. In case you forgot what we
learned in מסכת נזיר *Masechet Nazir*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* reminds us the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s take that he was a נזיר *Nazir* and right,
and therefore he was allowed to shave his hair, נזיר עולם *Nazir
Olam*, shave his hair once a year.
Anyway, sounds ridiculous, but in modern presidential campaigns, hair is often
hair and height, very important, exactly, that's a very good point. Yep.
Okay.
אבן המלך *Even Hamelech* a standard weight.
Like film, right?
They say like?
Yeah, a king stone, I don't know. It's sort of like שקל
הקודש *Shekel Hakodesh* or something. Yeah, yeah, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
going to do a דרשה drasha *Derasha* on that, so let's take
a look. It says, תנא tana, אבן שאנשי טבריה ואנשי ציפורי שוקלים
בה *Tanna Even She'anshei Tveria Ve'anshei Tzipori Shoklim Bah*. So again, it's
some standard that was used to weigh by the people of Tiberias
and people of Tzipori. לפיכך נתלה בשערו *Lefikhakh Nitlah Besearo*. Because he
was נתגאה בשערו *Nitga'ah Besearo*, therefore it was the cause of his
downfall, hoisted by his own petard. שנאמר shenemar *Shenemar*, as it says,
ויקרא אבשלום Avshalom לפני עבדי דוד David ואבשלום רכב על הפרד *Vayikra
Avshalom Lifnei Avdei David Ve'avshalom Rochev Al Hapered*. This is when they
were fighting in the in the forest. ויבא הפרד תחת שובך האלה
הגדולה ויחזק ראשו באלה ויתלה בין השמים ובין הארץ והפרד אשר תחתיו
עבר *Vayavo Hapered Tachat Sovekh Ha'elah Hagedolah Vayechezak Rosho Va'elah Vayutalah Bein
Hashamayim Uvein Ha'aretz Ve'hapered Asher Tachtav Avar*, and it came went under
the sort of branches of the terebinth, some type of a tree,
the great and he it held his head in the elm, it
says ויחזק ראשו באלה *Vayechezak Rosho Va'elah* and his hair was caught
up in the in the branches of the tree, ויתלה בין השמים
ובין הארץ *Vayutalah Bein Hashamayim Uvein Ha'aretz*, and he was hovering like
suspended between heaven and earth, והפרד אשר תחתיו עבר *Ve'hapered Asher Tachtav
Avar*, and the the donkey or what is it? It's a donkey,
פרד *Pered*. Mule. Mule. The mule passed under him, just kept on
going. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so שקל סייפרא *Shakal Saifeirah*,
he took a sword, בעי למיפסקיה *Ba'ei Lemifsekeih*, he wanted to cut
his hair. I mean this is crazy, right? How could he why
was he so stuck? Like just cut it, you know? So okay,
maybe he didn't have his sword on him, but anyway the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says no, he took a sword and he wanted to
cut his hair. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל באותה שעה נבקעה שאול מתחתיו
*Tanna D'vei Rabbi Yishmael Be'otah Sha'ah Nifke'ah Sheol Mitachtav*. At that moment
the depths opened up beneath him. וירגז המלך ויעל על עליית השער
ויבך *Vayirgaz Hamelech Vaya'al Al Aliyat Hasha'ar Vayeivk*. So presumably somehow the
being afraid of the depth or whatever, it's not exactly clear but
that somehow prevented him from cutting his hair, doesn't exactly connect the
dots. He was afraid he'd fall down into it. Oh, that's a
good oh okay yeah yeah oh that's a good point, I got
it. Oh, that's a good idea. No no you're right, you're right,
you're right. Obvious I wasn't thinking about that, I wasn't thinking.
Okay right, he can't now cut his hair because now he's going
to fall into the depths. Thank you very much. וירגז המלך ויעל
על עליית השער *Vayirgaz Hamelech Vaya'al Al Aliyat Hasha'ar*. Now after basically
יואב Yoav *Yoav* killed him, then the king his death was reported
and then the King David went up and he went to the
gate, ויבך וכה אמר בלכתו *Vayeivk Vekho Amar Belekhto* and he cried
and this is what he said, בני beni אבשלום Avshalom בני בני
אבשלום Avshalom. *Bni Avshalom Bni Bni Avshalom*, my son Absalom, my son,
מי יתן מותי אני תחתיך אבשלום Avshalom בני בני *Mi Yitein Muti
Ani Tachtecha Avshalom Bni Bni*, had I only died in your stead,
אבשלום בני בני *Avshalom Bni Bni*. והמלך לאט את פניו ויזעק המלך
קול גדול *Ve'hamelech Laat Et Panav Vayizak Hamelech Kol Gadol*, right and
the and he was crying and he cried out a great cry,
בני אבשלום אבשלום בני בני *Bni Avshalom Avshalom Bni Bni*. Wow, that's
a lot of בני אבשלום *Bni Avshalom*.
Wow can I just say one thing? Yes. I think this is
the saddest פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* in the תנ"ך Tanakh.
*Tanakh*. Yeah. Extremely sad. The sense of, you know, no matter what.
Right,
right. It's just really sad.
Yep. Thank you. Yep.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, הני תמניא בני למה *Hanei Tmanya
Bni Lama*? There's seven my son my son, and as Doe said
right that's what makes it so terribly poignant is you know is
with all that he had rebelled and all of that, right, just
that he's still his son. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, oh
הני תמניא *Hanei Tmanya*, excuse me, eight. So excuse me I was
jumping ahead to the next point. These are eight בני'ס *Bni's*. So
So what is the point of all that repetition other than to
express that grief, which it does so poignantly? So שבעה דאסקיה משבעה
מדורי גיהנום Gehenom. because now אבשלום was in the lowest depths of
גיהנום. Gehenom, So seven times, seven of those בניs raised him up
from the
seven depths of גיהנום, Gehenom each one raising him up a little
bit closer. ואידך ve'idach now the last one, איכא דאמרי דקרב רישיה
לגבי גופיה, ika de'amri dekarvei reishei legabei gufei, some say his head
was that at least what he did was he reconnected his head
to his body because his head was severed, right? He was when
he was killed. Although I don't think it says that in the
פסוקים. psukim. It says he was
smote by darts, and then it says and then the ten soldiers
it said smote him, but I don't think it ever says his
head was severed from his body. Okay. ואיכא דאמרי דאיתיה לעלמא דאתי,
ve'ika de'amri de'ayeitei le'alma de'atei, no, he even was able through his
prayer דוד David to bring him to עולם הבא. Olam Haba. It
is interesting also to see some of the myths or stories or
whatever that grew up after the death of the שבתי צבי, Shabtai
Tzvi, and like how much there was these myths about how did
people prayed to raise him up of גיהנום Gehenom, and bring him
to עולם הבא Olam Haba and so on, he is such a
powerful character that he has remained very much present in the imagination
of the people, couldn't accept with all of his sin that that
would be the end of the story. So anyway, here as well
the גמרא Gemara is struggling with this question about whether ultimately דוד
David was able to bring him to עולם הבא. Olam Haba.
I mean, this is an earlier question in terms of efficacy of
prayer.
So תוספות Tosfos raises that question. תוספות Tosfos says we will do
this very quickly again where we have a lot of גמרא Gemara
in a very little time. But תוספות Tosfos take a look at
just one line of תוספות, Tosfos, דאיתיה לעלמא דאתי, de'ayeitei le'alma de'atei,
תוספות Tosfos said, וקשיא הא אמרו בחלק ברא מזכי אבא אבא לא
מזכי ברא, vekasheh ha'amru becheilek bra mezakei aba aba lo mezakei bra,
that a son can bring merit to the father, a son's deeds
can bring benefit the father's soul. That is the question, the father
not the son. So he says, well what about all of this?
The father is מזכה mezake the son. So if you just skip
to the end, תוספות Tosfos says like this, he
says ועוד ve'od he says, first of all he says, אבשלום לא
עבד עבודת כוכבים, Avshalom lo avad avodat kochavim, so maybe if he
wasn't עובד עבודה זרה, oved avoda zara, he still is able to
be redeemed by the father as opposed to other cases. And אינמי
מצי לומר הא דאמר אבא לא מזכי ברא היינו משום כבוד האב
אין מונין מלמנותו עם רשעים
בלא תפילה, inami matzi lomar had'amar aba lo mezakei bra hainu mishum
kvod ha'av ein monin milimnoto im reshaim belo tfila, that just means
out of deference and respect to the father that's not going to
prevent labeling the son a רשע rasha if the son is a
רשע. rasha. אבל תפילה מועלת ודוד התפלל
על אבשלום. aval tfila mo'eles ve'David hitpaleil al Avshalom. But it still
is very interesting even with all of that, what does prayer of
a different person do for the soul of the sinner who died?
How is that related?
What?
That's the whole point of קדיש.
kaddish. Well exactly, but there the thought is that plays in with
the ברא מזכי אבא, bra mezakei aba, because there the thought is
that because the son is מקדש שם שמים, mekadish shem shamayim, so
therefore ultimately that's indirect שכר s'char that accrues to that dead person
because the dead person brought into the world this child who now
is doing these good things, so ultimately it is somewhat attributable to
them.
Well that's true, but the classic is, but yes, there the idea
is that if somebody is doing good deeds and somehow through this
other person, resulting through, somehow it accrues back to them as opposed
to just praying for somebody's soul, it is a different concept, doing
good deeds as opposed to praying for somebody's soul. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
And also saying that it seems harder to get out of גיהנום,
Gehenom, if you will, than to go into, well he already he
just wants
עולם הבא.
Olam Haba. Yeah, because it is one thing to put you out
of the punishment, it is another thing to say you are righteous.
But it is easier, in other words, all was just one last
thing.
Well once you're not in גיהנום, there's only one more step to
go. He wasn't going to go to the highest level of עולם
הבא, Olam Haba, he'll go to the entry level of עולם הבא.
Olam Haba. Okay. Alright, so being in the middle is
purgatory. Actually, there is some idea about that even in the Jewish
sources as well. Purg- no, about purgatory, כף הקלע. kaf hakela. Well
the גמרא Gemara speaks about
like the רשעים reshaim are like, it is even going to have
a name for it because it's like a temporary state, it is
for
like twelve months until they're finally judged anyway, it's a גמרא Gemara
in ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. Where was I? Okay. ואבשלום לקח ויצב לו בחייו. Va'Avshalom lakach
vayatziv lo bechayav. So now this is what's reported in the תנ"ך.
Tanakh Well that's true. This is what's reported in the תנ"ך Tanakh
after his death, it says אבשלום had already in his life taken
and created a monument for himself because he said I don't have
any children so this will be a monument for me and it
was called יד אבשלום. Yad Avshalom. That's like what the תורה Torah
reports, the
תנ"ך Tanach. the שמואל Shmuel reports after his death that he had
already created this monument for himself in his life. So the גמרא
Gemara. says מאי לקח? mai lakach? What does it mean he had
taken? אמר ריש לקיש שלקח מקח רע לעצמו. Amar Reish Lakish shelakach
mekach ra le'atzmo. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לקח, Mai Lakach,
what does it mean he had taken? אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish
Lakish שלקח מקח רע לעצמו. she'lakach mekach ra le'atzmo. So as like
ויקח קרח, Vayikach Korach, right? It's using it more metaphorically. He had
made a bad investment. Now what did it mean that he had
predicted his own death because he bought a monument for himself, or
did it just mean this whole undertaking was a מקח רע mekach
ra presumably. Okay. את מצבת אשר בעמק המלך, Et matzevat asher be'emek
hamelech, the monument in the Valley of the King. אמר רבי חנינא
בר פפא, Amar Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa, בעצה עמוקה של מלכו של
עולם, be'eitzah amukah shel malko shel olam, ultimately this was all the
divine plan. We sort of saw that earlier as well, you know,
with תמר Tamar and יהודה, Yehuda, and this was all sort of
following... there was another place also the גמרא Gemara said that this
was all sort of because of the divine plan. Anyway, who where
does the גמרא Gemara say that about before? I'm forgetting. People remember
that? Anyway. Okay, שמשון, Shimshon, I think, right? Was it שמשון? Shimshon?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. שמשון. Shimshon. Yeah, no, no, but it's yeah, but
no matter... but his running after the non-Jewish women and ultimately right,
all of that was even though there's the בחירה חופשית bechirah chofshit
it was all also the divine plan. So here too, it was
all the divine plan because if you look at רש״י, Rashi, he
says של הקדוש ברוך הוא שהוא בעולם שגזר על דוד כן במעשה
בת שבע. shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu she'hu be'olam she'gazar al David ken
be'ma'aseh Bat Sheva. Right? So in the sin of בת שבע, Bat
Sheva, right? דוד was told, you know, that you know your... you
know somebody will rise up from your house and rebel against you
and so on. So not taking away from אבשלום's בחירה חופשית, bechirah
chofshit, but somehow it also worked with the divine plan.
דכתיב, De'chtiv, הנני מקים עליך רעה מביתך, hineni mekim alecha ra'ah mi'beitecha,
I will raise up an evil from within your house. כיוצא בדבר
אתה אומר, Ki'yotzei badavar at omer, similarly you say, וישלחהו מעמק חברון
ויבא שכמה. Vayishlachehu me'emek Chevron vayavo Shechemah. This is with יוסף Yosef
and the brothers when he was sent to check on his brothers.
אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא, Amar Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa, בעצה עמוקה,
be'eitzah amukah, עמק emek here again, the deep strategy or you know
plan of אותו צדיק שקבור בחברון, oto tzadik she'kavur be'Chevron, that righteous
person who is buried in חברון Chevron which is אברהם. Avraham. דכתיב,
De'chtiv, ידוע תדע כי גר יהיה זרעך. yado'a teda ki ger yihyeh
zar'acha. So this is ultimately the fulfillment of the God's sort of
decree or promise to אברהם Avraham about the enslavement or the estrangement
of the children in a foreign land, and this was all to
make sure that that would come about. Okay, back to אבשלום. כי
אמר, Ki amar, yeah, little tiny problem here about השגחה פרטית hashgacha
pratit and בחירה חופשית, bechirah chofshit, moving on. כי אמר אין לי
בן. Ki amar ein li ben.
Yes. Did the distance to this have to do with his feeling
of guilt as it came about...
oh that's an interesting point. Maybe that sense about that guilt has
caused at some level a knowledge that all of this was a
punishment for his sin. That's a very good point. That's a very
good point. כי אמר אין לי בן, Ki amar ein li ben,
אבשלום erected this monument because he said I have no
son. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולא הוו ליה בנים, ve'lo havu
leh banim?, he didn't have children, sons? והכתיב, V'hachtiv, ויולדו לאבשלום שלושה
בנים ובת אחת. vayivaldu le'Avshalom shelosha banim ve'bat achat. This is what
it reported like before this whole story. He had three sons and
one daughter. אמר רבי יצחק בר אבדימי, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Abdimi,
שלא היה לו בן הגון למלכות. shelo hayah lo ben hagun lemalkhut.
No, he didn't have a son that was fit to sort of
take over the kingship for him so maybe he figured although that's
interesting because that means that even way back then when he had
made the monument he was already planning on becoming king and rebelling
because it didn't say when he made the monument. Okay. But he
did not feel that he would have a child that would carry
his name with the same type of fame or recognition or so
they're renown. So therefore he had to make for himself this monument.
רב חסדא אמר גמירי, Rav Chisda amar gemiri, we have a tradition
that כל השורף תבואתו של חבירו, kol hasoref tevuato shel chavero, anybody
who burns his friend's wheat, אינו מניח בן ליורשו, eino mani'ach ben
leyorsho, his child will never survive to inherit him. I guess because
you know there's...
yes, it means it literally. So he had a children, a child,
but he knew his children had died or he knew they would
die. How do we know? Because there was a story of אבשלום
burning יואב's Yoav wheat as we're about to see. But just to
say something about this other than that it seems to be like
constructed to fit the fact, you know, to serve as an explanation.
You know, it seems to be an idea. Like you know we
speak about like the fruit of your labors, your children, fruit of
the womb, fruit of your hands, fruit of your labors. You know
you spend all this time planting the seeds, obviously there's a whole
seed and sprouting and growing and whatever, and somebody else comes and
he cuts them all down. Right? So burnt them down. So so
as you burned down somebody else's, you know, exactly. That's my point.
It's a מידה כנגד מידה. mida kineged mida So your progeny will
be cut down.
Okay. ואיהו קליה דיואב, ve'ihu kali de'Yoav, and he burned down יואב's
Yoav wheat. דכתיב, De'chtiv, it says, this was when אבשלום had been
accepted to move back to ירושלים Yerushalayim but the king had refused
to receive him. And he was trying to get יואב Yoav to
intercede on his behalf for the king to get the king to
receive him and יואב Yoav was not responding to אבשלום. So in
order to get יואב's Yoav attention he burned down יואב's wheat field.
Okay. ויאמר אל עבדיו ראו חלקת יואב אל ידי ולו שם שעורים
לכו והציתוה באש, Vayomer el avadav re'u chelkat Yoav el yadi ve'lo
sham se'orim lechu vehatzituha va'esh, go burn it by fire, ויציתו עבדי
אבשלום את החלקה באש. vayatzitu avdei Avshalom et hachelka va'esh.
And they burned down the field with fire. Okay. And ultimately that
led to him being raising up back in status and ultimately enabled
him to rebel later on in the story. Of course I had
to reread this last night because I totally forgot the context. I
said to אדורה, Adora, I said you know it's very frustrating, the
גמרא Gemara assumes that we know תנך.
Anyway, okay. All right. Yes.
Do you mean like literally the kid will die or just like
you know he won't inherit?
I don't know. Okay, וכן לעניין הטובה. vechein linyan hatovah. Now we
switch, we leave אבשלום and we go back to the משנה Mishna,
that says the same way there's מידה כנגד מידה mida kineged mida
for bad, there's מידה כנגד מידה mida kineged mida for good, and
it brings the example of מרים Miriam that she hovered over by
משה Moshe for one hour and in the end בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael waited for her for seven days when she was smitten. Right.
So that's what we want to say. מכדי, Michdi, what do you
mean? It's just like, you know, the מידה כנגד מידה mida kineged
mida? for good is the same as for bad. התם חד שעתא,
Hatam chada sha'ata, there it was just one hour and that she,
I'm sorry, how can you say that's מידה כנגד מידה? mida kineged
mida She only waited for one hour, הכא שבעה ימי hacha shiv'ah
yomei and בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael waited for her for seven days?
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אימא ולעניין הטובה אינה כן. eima ulinyan hatovah
einah kein.
No, you should read the משנה, but for מידה טובה mida tovah
it's not like this, it's even more. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei
Rava, הכא וכן לעניין הטובה קתני. hacha vechein linyan hatovah katani. What
do you mean? You can't just change the גירסא. girsa. It says
the same way there's מידה כנגד מידה mida kineged mida for bad,
it's the same for good. It's not saying it's different for good.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לעניין הטובה דבאותה מידה ולעולם מידה טובה
מרובה ממידת פורענות. linyan hatovah de'be'ota mida ule'olam mida tovah merubah mimiddat
puranut.
So here's what it means. It means the concept of measure for
measure is the same for good and for bad. That's the way
they're saying. When it comes to the quantity of it, you know,
the amount, so then the מידה טובה mida tovah is greater than
מידת פורענות. midat puranut. But the fundamental idea of מידה כנגד מידה
mida kineged mida. applies to both, but מידה טובה mida tovah is
the amount is many more manifold over what was done. Okay. ותתצב
אחותו מרחוק. Vatitatzav achoto merachok. So now there's a cute little תוספות
Tosafot and he says, so, so,
no not that one. Okay, so if you take a look at
תוספות, Tosafot, it says the following: מרים המתינה שעה אחת. Miriam himtina
sha'ah achat. So תוספות Tosafot says, לאו דווקא שעה
אלא
שליש
שעה או רביע.
lav davka
sha'ah ela shalish sha'ah o revia.
It must have really been only like a quarter of an hour
or 20 minutes. דתניא בתוספתא מידה טובה מרובה ממידת פורענות
על אחת חמש מאות. detanya beTosefta mida tovah merubah mimiddat puranut al
achat chamesh mei'ot. It says it's a 500
times. So מידה כנגד מידה. mida kineged mida. So figure out how
many hours there are in seven days. Let's see.
140, 28,
168, right? So if she waited one hour and that was only
168 times they waited seven days, so it has to be they
waited really a third of an hour, right? Because three times 168
is 500 essentially, right? 485, right,
almost exactly 500. So it has to really be, I don't know
why it says או רביע, o revia, it was really only a
third of an hour. Okay. אבל קשיא לרבי והא במרגלים נפרע מהם
יום לשנה יום לשנה. aval kashya leRebbi veha bemeraglim nifra mehem yom
leshana yom leshana.
And that's 365 to one. And that's מידת פורענות. midat puranut. So
that's not מידה כנגד מידה. mida kineged mida, It's bigger. I'm sorry,
it's smaller than 500, but it's not that's true, it's smaller than
500 but it's still not exactly מידה כנגד מידה, middah k'neged middah.
right? It's not one to one as opposed to one to 500.
Here it's 365 to one. אם כן היתה מרובה מידת פורענות ממידה
טובה של מרים. im kein hayta merubah midat puranut mimida tovah shel
Miriam.
No, he says it's more than מרים, Miriam, but I don't get
it. They're right because it's only 365 to one. I don't get
how יום לשנה yom leshana is more than the one for מרים.
Miriam. I don't get that question. Anyway, but the point is it's
not one to one certainly. והא פרק קמא דחגיגה דדרש רבי יוחנן
אותי יום יום ידרשון, veha perek kama deChagiga dedarash Rebbi Yochanan oti
yom yom yidrashun, שכל העוסק בתורה אפילו יום אחד כאילו עוסק כל
השנה כולה. shekol ha'osek baTorah afilu yom echad ke'ilu osek kol hashana
kula.
So there you get, you also get the 365 multiplier. Right, it's
equal. וכן במידת פורענות כתיב במספר הימים אשר תרתם את הארץ. vechein
bemidat puranut ktiv bemispar hayamim asher tartem et ha'aretz. The גמרא Gemara
there exactly equates them. אלמא דשוין נינהו. alma deshavin ninhu.
So is it מידה טובה mida tovah more than מידת פורענות? midat
puranut? Is it the same? Is it one to one? Is it
one to a multiplier? We'll leave the math to God. Anyway, back
to the גמרא. Gemara Okay. מידה טובה מרובה ממידת פורענות. mida tovah
merubah mimiddat puranut. ותתצב אחותו מרחוק. Vatitatzav achoto merachok.
His sister sort of stood from afar. Back to now we get
the focus on the מרים Miriam story. So, and by the way,
this is going to be an opening for us now for the
remainder of the דף pretty much to do דרשות drashot on the
whole story, not just of מרים, Miriam, but all of משה Moshe
and מצרים Mitzrayim and the whole thing. So like, you know, סוטה
is like the motherlode of like most of the אגדתא. Agadata. I
don't know, it'll be interesting like what percentage of אגדתא Agadata in
ש"ס Shas is in מסכת סוטה. Masechet Sotah. Exactly. ותתצב אחותו מרחוק.
Vatitatzav achoto merachok. אמר רבי יצחק,
Amar
Rebbi
Yitzchak, פסוק זה כולו על שם שכינה נאמר. pasuk zeh kulo al
shem Shechina ne'emar.
This was all that the divine presence was hovering there to protect
משה. Moshe. It wasn't just like מרים Miriam was, like you know
God was there to protecting משה. Moshe. שנאמר, she'ne'emar, okay, נאמר ותתצב,
ne'emar vatitatzav, to stand. וכתיב דכתיב, u'ktiv dechtiv, ויבא ה' ויתיצב. vayavo
Hashem vayityatzav.
So that's a verb that's used by God. אחותו, achoto, sister, דכתיב,
dechtiv, אמור לחכמה אחותי את. emor lachochma achoti at. If
you know, say to wisdom you are my sister and wisdom is
like sort of like God, you know, represents like God created wisdom,
or something very close to God, you know, from the Kabbalists see
some of these represent I think different ספירות, sefirot,
but I'm not allowed to tell you that. Okay. מרחוק, merachok, from
distance, דכתיב, dechtiv, מרחוק ה'
נראה לי. merachok Hashem nirah li.
God appeared to me from a distance. לדעת, lada'at, to know, דכתיב
כי אל דעות ה'. dechtiv ki el de'ot Hashem. So מה דכתיב,
ma dich'shiv, מה, ma, to know what דכתיב, dich'shiv, מה השם אלקיך
שואל ממך. ma Hashem elokecha shoel mimcha. יעשה, Yeaseh, will be done,
דכתיב כי לא יעשה השם אלקים דבר. dich'shiv ki lo yeaseh Hashem
Elokim davar. לו, Lo, to him, דכתיב dich'shiv ויקרא לו השם שלום.
vayakrah lo Hashem shalom. Okay,
so every single one of those words is used in conjunction with
God. I mean, God appears a lot in תנ״ך, Tanakh, so a
lot of words are used in conjunction with God. Okay, ויקם מלך
חדש על מצרים. vayakam melech chadash al Mitzrayim. So now let's talk
about the about the whole story with משה Moshe and בני ישראל.
Bnei Yisrael. A new king arose over Egypt. רב ושמואל, Rav u'Shmuel,
חד אמר, chad amar, חדש ממש, chadash mamash, וחד אמר vechad amar
שנתחדשו גזירותיו. shenitchadshu gzeirotav.
One said he literally was a new king, the other one says
he no, he changed his whole approach towards dealing with
because we talked about מרים Miriam hovering over משה. Moshe. מרים? Miriam?
We were just talking about פרעה. Paroh.
Yeah, well now we're going to give the whole context of the
whole story. This is the lead up to it. Right. It's an
opportunity to to talk about the whole story. שנתחדשו גזירותיו, shenitchadshu gzeirotav,
his whole approach changed towards בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. מאן דאמר man
d'amar חדש ממש, chadash mamash, דכתיב dich'shiv חדש. chadash.
What do you mean? It says a new king. ומאן דאמר u'man
d'amar שנתחדשו גזירותיו, shenitchadshu gzeirotav, דלא כתיב dilo ksiv וימת וימלוך, vayamot
vayimloch,
because it never said the old king died. So that means that
it was not really a new king. It was just a new
approach. I see, okay. אשר לא ידע את יוסף, asher lo yada
et Yosef, who did not know יוסף. Yosef. דהוה דמי dehavah dami
כמאן דלא ידע ליה כלל. keman dilo yadalei klal. He acted as
if he never knew him. ויאמר אל עמו. vayomer el amo. He
said to his nation. הנה עם בני ישראל. hinei am Bnei Yisrael.
So behold the nation Israel. תנא, הוא התחיל בעצה תחילה. hu hitchil
be-eitzah techila. He was the one that was the instigator of the
whole plan against בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. לפיכך לקה תחילה. lefichach lakah
techila. Again, here's the מידה כנגד מידה. middah k'neged middah. He was
the one that was smitten first. הוא התחיל בעצה תחילה hu hitchil
be-eitzah techila דכתיב dich'shiv ויאמר אל עמו, vayomer el amo, לפיכך לקה
תחילה lefichach lakah techila he was smitten first דכתיב dich'shiv ובך ובעמך
ובכל עבדיך יעלו הצפרדעים. uvecha uve'amcha uvechol avadecha ya'alu hatzfarde'im.
So he was the one that was first hit with the first
with the plague. Okay, הבה נתחכמה לו. hava nitchachma lo. Come, let
us like scheme against them or plan regarding them. להם מיבעי ליה,
lahem mibayei lei, should have said them. Now, actually, it says עם
בני ישראל am Bnei Yisrael and עם am is in the singular,
but the גמרא Gemara is going to somehow assume you're talking about
the people, you should be talking about them in the plural. So
it's going to focus a lot on the singular of this verse.
Okay, it should have said להם, lahem, not לו. lo. אמר רבי
חמא ברבי חנינא, amar Rabbi Chama b'Rabbi Chanina, בואו ונחכם למושיען של
ישראל. bo'u venitchacham lemoshi'an shel Yisrael. No,
let's outfox God. לו, lo, נתחכמה לו, nitchachma lo, the
him, the him with a capital H. Okay, the Savior of Israel.
במה נידונם? bameh nidonam? מנידונם. minidonam. Now, how should we what are
we going to go ahead and oppress בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael in
a way that God won't be able to pay us back? Okay,
so I mean, or the God of Israel, מושיען של ישראל, moshi'an
shel Yisrael, like that that God won't be able to pay us
back. And this obviously is going to assume that פרעה Paroh already
knows the principle that we've been talking about of מידה כנגד מידה.
middah k'neged middah, So therefore, נידונם באש, nidonam b'esh, should we oppress
them, or smite them with a fire? כתיב כי הנה השם באש
יבוא. ksiv ki hinei Hashem b'esh yavo. No, God will smite us
with a fire.
וכתיב ve'chsiv כי באש השם נשפט. ki va'esh Hashem nishpat.
בחרב, becherev, should we should we go ahead and smite them by
the sword? כתיב ובחרבו את כל בשר, ksiv uvcharbo et kol basar,
same פסוק pasuk in ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. אלא בואו ונידונם במים. ela bo'u
venidonam bamayim. Let's use water to smite them, right? Throw the kids
into the into the נלוס. Nilus. שכבר נשבע הקדוש ברוך הוא שאינו
מביא מבול לעולם. shekevar nishba Hakadosh Baruch Hu she'eino meivi mabul l'olam.
God had sworn that he won't bring a flood to the world,
שנאמר she'ne'emar, כי מי נח זאת לי כי נשבעתי מעבור מי נח
עוד על הארץ. ki mei Noach zot li ki nishbati me'avor mei
Noach od al ha'aretz. והן אינם יודעים, vehein einam yodim, so they
thought they were going to outfox God because they knew the principle
of מידה כנגד מידה, mida k'neged mida and they did not know
שעל כל העולם כולו אינו מביא. she'al kol ha'olam kulo eino meivi.
No, he won't bring a flood of the whole world. אבל על
אומה אחת הוא מביא, aval al umah achat hu meivi, for פרעה
Paroh to go ahead and drown one nation. אי נמי, i nami,
הוא אינו מביא, hu eino meivi, he won't bring it on them.
אבל הם באים ונופלים בתוכו, aval hem ba'im venoflim betocho, they all
want to run into the ים סוף Yam Suf at fair business.
Okay, וכן הוא אומר vechein hu omer ומצרים נסים לקראתו, u'Mitzrayim nasim
likrato,
they were running to to greet it. So they ran into it.
It wasn't God who did it. All right, it wasn't God who
brought it on them.
דהיינו דאמר רבי אלעזר, de'hainu de'amar Rabbi Elazar, מאי דכתיב mai dich'shiv
כי בדבר אשר זדו עליהם, ki vadavar asher zadu aleihem,
because in the matter that they had properly like זדו, zadu, it
probably means they had planned against them, schemed against
them.
No, but this
is even more than that. So the גמרא Gemara
is saying דכתיב, dich'shiv, it's
a cooking metaphor. All right, well that's what the
that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. בקדירה שבישלו בה
נתבשלו. bekdeira shebishlu bah nitbashlu.
In the pot that they cooked, again with, you know, use water
and cooking something in water, right? So it's also probably connected to
the water metaphor. In the very pot that they that they cooked
or that they brought about, a project to kill בני ישראל, Bnei
Yisrael, oppress בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, they themselves were cooked. Hoist by
their own petard again. מאי משמע דהאי זדו לשנא דקדירה? mai mashma
dehai zadu lishna dekdeira? How do you know that זדו zadu is
a language of a of a pot? דכתיב ויזד יעקב נזיד. dich'shiv
vayazed Yaakov nazid. Okay, there you go. So it means to be
cooked. They were cooked in their own pot. Yes.
Is this a rabbinic reinterpretation that השם Hashem that Pharaoh is looking
through the that he believes in God but well I think
it says מושיען של ישראל moshian shel Yisrael
which is why I switched it from God to the the Jewish
God, you know, the God of Israel. Like, you know, in a
in a poly- in a polytheistic context, a person
who's gonna help Israel?
Oh maybe. That could be. But I thought Pharaoh says from the
very beginning I
don't recognize השם Hashem what are
you you know
back to work.
Yeah but I don't recognize the authority of the authority well like
that is a good point meaning even in that context if he
doesn't recognize the authority of that God to tell him I mean
in a polytheistic world you could believe in other nations' Gods as
well but I mean I don't believe that that your God has
the authority has that type of power over me then why is
he scheming against it? Yeah. All right, it's once again where a
מדרש Midrash doesn't exactly fit with the פשט, pshat, let alone that
it's quoting פסוקים pesukim in ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. But you are right that
it's deeper than the quoting פסוק pasuk from ישעיהו Yeshayahu which are
obviously anachronistic because this sort of changes the whole narrative in a
profound way. It sort of like makes Pharaoh from the very outset
know God and be trying to scheme against it which is a
very different type of a dynamic than refusing to recognize. So that's
a yeah that's a really good point. All right, so גמרא Gemara
says like this. אבא Abba okay little אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba
another famous מדרש. Midrash. אמר רבי סימאי שלושה היו באותה עצה Amar
Rabbi Simai shlosha hayu beosah eitzah there were three that were in
that little council to plan against בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So בלעם
ואיוב ויתרו. Bilam v'Iyov v'Yisro. בלעם איוב ויתרו Bilam Iyov v'Yisro meaning
other than Pharaoh those were his that was his council of advisors.
בלעם שיעץ Bilam sheya'atz so besides although before we said it was
Pharaoh's initiative now we're saying בלעם Bilam was an advisor because we
know that's what בלעם Bilam does. He gives advice, you know, בא
ואייעצך אשר יעשה העם הזה לעמך באחרית הימים, Bo v'iyaatzcha asher yaaseh
ha'am hazeh l'amecha b'acharis hayamim, right?
And you know and by the and by the בנות מדין Bnos
Midyan it says הן הנה היו לבני ישראל בדבר בלעם. Hen heinah
hayu livnei Yisrael bidvar Bilam.
So בלעם Bilam is the one that behind the scenes gives advice,
you know, to hurt other nations. So בלעם Bilam was the advisor.
נהרג Neherag he ultimately was killed later in the whole story with
the you know the war against מדין. Midyan. איוב ששתק Iyov sheshatak
איוב Iyov was silent. He didn't want he didn't agree but he
didn't have the courage to go up against Pharaoh. So נידון בייסורין
nidon b'yisurin that explains now we understand why איוב Iyov suffered. You
didn't know the whole book of איוב Iyov doesn't tell you why
he suffered. Now we know because he was silent. Okay which has
to do with but it's very important right because it has to
do with being a silent enabler, you know, and how what's you
know all what is it all evil has to do to flourish
is for good men to stand by and be quiet or something
like that.
Right right like that ברייתא braisa of those חכמים Chachamim as well.
That's also right exactly there's that exact oh thank you right I
knew that it was yeah there's a beautiful parallel to that ברייתא
braisa of the חכמים Chachamim talking about רומי Romi and one of
them sort of you know one of them praised רומי Romi and
the other was silent and the other was silent and the third
one criticized רומי. Romi. Exactly and they all right right that's excellent
that's at the beginning of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah exactly thank you.
All right so but it also does speak about the about you
know how you essentially through your silence you're also collaborating. And it
also continues with בלעם Bilam
if I remember correctly the גמרא says that he's נידון nidon with
like yeah yeah okay let's not go there.
All right let's not go there. Yes. Okay so he was נידון
בייסורין nidon b'yisurin and יתרו שברח Yisro shebarach זכו מבני בניו שישבו
בלשכת הגזית. zachu mibnei banav sheyeshvu b'lishkas hagazis. He ran away which
I guess is the best you could do you know he which
is essentially I think he did protest though. Yeah but essentially it's
why did he run away essentially he's protesting and he ran away
or it's implicit in his running away
or he protested and he ran away. And he took his whole
family. And he took his whole family right well
for right well I don't know maybe he was commuting I don't
know all right but anyway anyway he ran away and then he
went to מדין. Midyan. So זכו מבני בניו שישבו בלשכת הגזית zachu
mibnei banav sheyeshvu b'lishkas hagazis eventually his descendants dwelt you know were
part of the Sanhedrin and were in the chamber of the hewn
stone there in the Sanhedrin in in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
שנאמר ממשפחות סופרים Shene'emar mimishpachos sofrim the family of scribes ישבי יעבץ
yoshvei Yavetz יעבץ Yavetz was a great sage תרעתים שמעתים שוכתים המה
Tirasim Shimasim Suchasim heima
so רש"י Rashi tries to give a דרש drash on those words
we're not worried about that המה הקינים heima HaKeinim these are the
Kenites הבאים מחמת haba'im m'Chamas
who descended from חמת Chamas אבי בית רכב. avi Beis Rechav. וכתיב
ובני קיני חותן משה Uchsiv uvnei Keini chosen Moshe and there so
the Kenites were ultimately you know משה'ס Moshe's from יתרו Yisro because
it's identified as the father-in-law of יתרו Yisro and here they were
they were the they were the scribes and ישבי יעבץ yoshvei Yavetz
is also associated with sitting in the you know members of the
Sanhedrin.
So I guess the מידה כנגד מידה Midah kineged midah meaning like
that was a good advice to do right therefore his oh they
gave advice.
They were the advisors. Oh that's interesting. Okay that's interesting I guess
so yep I hear that. Okay. All right. ונלחם בנו ועלה מן
הארץ V'nilcham banu v'alah min ha'aretz and we will and they will
and they will fight wage war against us and rise up from
the land. All right the גמרא says ועלינו מיבעי ליה v'aleinu mibai
lei the if here if a nation you're afraid of a nation
rising up and waging war you should be afraid of be driven
from the land, not that they'll just leave. Of course I don't
know, I mean even so, you know, if you're this, you know,
this world power of Egypt, you're really afraid that this nation is
going to conquer you? You might just be afraid that they'll, that
they'll leave. But anyway the גמרא says if you're afraid they should
have been, it should have been we will rise up from the
land, that they'll drive us from the land. דעלינו מן הארץ מבעי
ליה. d'aleinu min ha'aretz mibayei lei. So it says, אמר רבי אבא
בר כהנא Amar Rabbi Abba Bar Kahana כאדם שמקלל את עצמו ותולה
קללתו בחבירו. k'adam shem'kalel et atzmo v'toleh klalato b'chaveiro. It's sort of
like you don't want to say something bad about yourself so you
say it about somebody else. You mean we'll be driven from the
land, but you don't want to say that so you say they'll
go out from the land. Exactly. That's why when the גמרא wants
to say bad things that will befall ישראל Yisrael it says things
that will befall שונאי ישראל. sonei Yisrael. Okay. וישימו עליו שרי מסים.
Vayasimu alav sarei misim.
They placed upon them, again they're using the singular as a nation,
you know, taskmasters. עליהם מבעי ליה aleihem mibayei lei again the גמרא
assumes it should be in the plural. So the גמרא says, תנא
דבי רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון Tana d'vei Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon מלמד
שהביאו מלבן ותלאו לו לפרעה בצוארו. melamed she'heviu malben v'talu lo l'Paroh
b'tzavaro. They brought a stone or a form of a brick and
they put it around, you know, hung it around פרעה's Paroh own
neck. So that's the וישימו עליו vayasimu alav on פרעה. Paroh. So
and he's like calling like it's a day like we want everybody
in the nation to come and to do some work for the
building of and you know in the Cecil B. DeMille film it's
the pyramids but that doesn't work according to the dating. And the
תורה Torah says ערי מסכנות, arei miskenot, you know which is like
treasure storehouses. Anyway we want everybody of the nation to come and
participate in this building project. Even פרעה's Paroh going to participate in
the building project. Everybody does it and then the next day as
we're going to see basically it's great, now you started building now
you can continue. למען ענותו בסבלותם.
L'ma'an
anoto b'sivlotam.
All right well we'll get to that. Anyway, okay, so שהביאו מלבן
ותלאו לפרעה בצוארו she'heviu malben v'talu l'Paroh b'tzavaro וכל אחד ואחד מישראל
שאמר להם איסטניס אני v'chol echad v'echad mi'Yisrael she'amar lahem istinis ani
anyone that said no I'm too refined to actually have to work
with bricks. אמרו לו כלום איסטניס אתה יותר מפרעה Amru lo klum
istinis ata yoter mi'Paroh are you more refined than פרעה? Paroh? So
they got everybody to work on that day. So שרי מסים sarei
misim a taskmasters. דבר שמשים לבנים Davar she'mesim l'venim
or whatever, something that creates forms. Meaning it again it's not a
taskmaster who's being a taskmaster to פרעה, Paroh, but it means a
form of a brick somehow. That's I don't know רשי, Rashi? I
didn't exactly get how רשי Rashi tied in what the word מסים
misim means to this context. Anyway but something that's used to form
a brick. למען ענותו, L'ma'an anoto, so in order to oppress him.
בסבלותם B'sivlotam in their, you know, burdens. ענותם מבעי ליה. anotam mibayei
lei. Now here actually the grammar is, it is a problem because
it should be either למען ענותו בסבלותו l'ma'an anoto b'sivloto
or למען ענותם בסבלותם. l'ma'an anotam b'sivlotam. It's a mixing of the
singular and the plural. So למען ענותו לפרעה l'ma'an anoto l'Paroh they
caused for that one day פרעה Paroh to be, you know, oppressed,
you know, or subjugate himself or lower himself. בסבלותם של ישראל. b'sivlotam
shel Yisrael. Ultimately to lead to the enslavement of Israel. So it
was ענותו anoto בסבלותם b'sivlotam for the sake of their, of their
enslavement. I don't understand, meaning like
פרעה Paroh was eventually punished? No.
No. On that one day וישימו עליו vayasimu alav they placed on
פרעה Paroh שרי מסים sarei misim this like type of however שרי
מסים sarei misim means, this type of a somebody, you know, this
form of a brick. למען ענותו L'ma'an anoto it made they oppressed
פרעה Paroh for that one day and it was בסבלותם b'sivlotam for
the sake of impressing Israel. It was a ruse. It was a
ruse. Okay. ויבן ערי מסכנות לפרעה. Vayiven arei miskenot l'Paroh. Then they
built these storehouses to פרעה. Paroh. So what's the word מסכנות? miskenot?
So the גמרא says רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. חד אמר שמסכנות את
בעליהן. Chad amar she'mesaknot et ba'aleihen. Now רשי Rashi says that this
is a more understood to be a general comment on undergoing building
projects. Okay, but also true for here. That you know when you
undergo build building projects it endangers the people involved in it. You
know there's a lot of deaths that happen during construction projects. וחד
אמר V'chad amar the other says שממסכנות את בעליהן. she'm'maskenot et ba'aleihen.
It turns the people poor. You know how often is it that
building projects run over and cost millions of dollars more than you
had budgeted it etc. דאמר מר כל העוסק בבנין מתמסכן. D'amar mar
kol ha'osek b'vinyan mitmasken. Anybody that's involved in these building projects ultimately
gets poor.
No, built a lot of money in real estate.
I know. I know. So it's interesting. I guess.
Donald Trump went bust.
Right. Right. Well, you know, Donald Trump went bust seven times or
something whatever it was. Okay. את פתום ואת רעמסס. Et Pitom v'et
Ra'amses. Okay. פתום Pitom and רעמסס. Ra'amses. What does this mean? רב
ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. חד אמר פתום שמה. Chad amar Pitom sh'ma. It
was all the same place. Its real name was פתום. Pitom. ולמה
נקרא שמה רעמסס? V'lama nikra sh'ma Ra'amses? רעמסס Ra'amses was descriptive. I
don't know why it says that. שראשון ראשון מתרוסס. She'rishon rishon mitroses.
That as soon as they would build it, every initial building would
like, you know, would tremble and would basically would shatter. Okay. וחד
אמר רעמסס שמה. V'chad amar Ra'amses sh'ma. It was called רעמסס. Ra'amses.
ולמה נקרא שמה פתום? V'lama nikra sh'ma Pitom? שראשון ראשון פי תהום
בולעו. she'rishon rishon pi tehom bola'o. Everything that they would build it
would immediately be swallowed up by the swamp. Reminds me of the...
עמק השרון. Emek HaSharon. Same thing. You see you've got a relevance.
I reminded me of the, of the skit from, from Monty Python.
I built the first
one and it and you know and it sunk. the guy building
castles on the swamp. And then the second one and that sunk
too. Anyway, whatever. Okay. All right. Anyway, so everything they would build,
it would all collapse. So I did hear once a very beautiful
דרשה drasha about that, about like that way of understanding the עבודת
פרך avodas parech is about what it means to be involved, exactly,
in labor that is completely purposeless, that in addition to the backbreaking
nature of it, right, the purposeless nature of it is supposedly disparaging,
right? So, you know, like it was... Sisyphus. Oh, Sisyphus. Yeah, that's
true. Right, right, right. You know, and like I mean sometimes, you
know like in like bootcamp or whatever they tell them, you know,
dig a hole and then, you know, now fill it up, you
know, and then dig a hole and whatever like just do a
whole thing which is serves no purpose. It's very demoralizing. Okay, okay,
yeah.
Because I want to get to the דרש drash because I mean
the פשט pshat works very well. A-Rameses' gonna...
Right, of course, of course. Okay, but which makes another point. Okay.
וכאשר יענו אתו כן ירבה וכן יפרץ, V'ka'asher ya'anu oto ken yirbeh
v'chen yifrotz,
as they would oppress again the singular him, so they would increase
and so they would, you know, spread out. כן רבו וכן פרצו
Ken rabu v'chen partzu it should have been: so they did increase
and they did spread out. What is it they will increase and
will spread out? אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, רוח הקודש מבשרתן.
Ruach Hakodesh mevasertan.
It's like the heavenly voice is coming out. וכאשר יענו אתו כן
ירבה וכן יפרץ. V'ka'asher ya'anu oto ken yirbeh v'chen yifrotz. You say,
you know, you're oppressing them, I'm saying so will they increase and
so will they, you know, and so will they spread out. So
you know, exactly counter, you know, the God's sort of directly countering
פרעה's Paro's plan.
I think there's another form which actually says it even sharper. אתה
אמרת פן ירבה אני אומר כן ירבה, Atah amarta pen yirbeh ani
omer ken yirbeh, right?
Which is again, right, exactly echoing פן ירבה, pen yirbeh, right? Okay.
Exactly. מידה
כנגד מידה
Midah kineged
midah, like the whole thing.
Exactly. מידה כנגד מידה, right, okay, yeah.
As the image of the, of the negative one as sort of
like subtraction and the positive one is like expansion, you know, in
terms of why one the negative one gets measured...
Oh, I see. Why the one is greater because blessing, blessing is
expansive in the same way punishment is contraction. Oh, that's a nice
idea. Okay. So ויקצו מפני
בני ישראל,
Vayakutzu mipnei
Bnei Yisrael, and they were disgusted from
the presence of בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, repulsed. מלמד שהיו דומים בעיניהם
כקוצים. Melamed she'hayu domim be'eineihem kekotzim. It was like, you know, it
was like just seeing ישראל Yisrael became like thorns in their eyes.
ויעבדו מצרים את בני ישראל בפרך, Vaya'avidu Mitzrayim et Bnei Yisrael befarech,
and they worked them with backbreaking labor. So רבי אליעזר אומר בפה
רך. Rabbi Eliezer omer bepeh rach. So they seduced them, a soft
voice, which is the whole way they got them to work on
that first day according to that מדרש. midrash. רבי שמואל בר נחמני
אומר בפריכה. Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani omer befrichah. No, it means with
crushing. וימררו את חייהם בעבדה קשה בחמר ובלבנים. Vayemareru et hayeihem ba'avodah
kashah bechomer uvilveinim. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, בתחלה בחמר ובלבנים, Batchilah bechomer
uvilveinim, first
they had them do the work with the brick and the mortar.
ולבסוף ובכל עבדה
בשדה, Ulevasof uvchol avodah basadeh, and eventually they had them do the
work in the field, which is not so clear, seems to me
fieldwork is less harsh than brick and mortar. But anyway, maybe it's
more exposed to the sun, I don't know. את כל עבודתם אשר
עבדו בהם בפרך, Et kol avodatam asher avdu bahem befarech, all of
the work that they made them work in with backbreaking work. אמר
רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani
amar Rabbi Yonatan, שהיו מחליפים מלאכת אנשים לנשים ומלאכת נשים לאנשים. She'hayu
machlifim melechet anashim lenashim umelechet nashim la'anashim. They made men do women's
work and women do men's work, again that's sort of the demoralizing
aspect of it. And it's just, you know, so רש"י says, where's
the רש"י? רש"י says, where is it? וזו קשה שלא היו רגילים
בכך. Vezu kashah shelo hayu regilim bekach. Right, they didn't have, they
were never accustomed to it, like, 'What am I...' you know.
Reminds me of סדום, Sodom, right?
Oh, what'd you say?
The original like social reform.
Yeah, but I think that the point more was that it was
like, you know, it was feminizing the men and, you know, masculinizing
the women and it was also
like you said, instead of doing the backbreaking work that you're accustomed
to, you're
going to have to sew some dresses.
Right. Sew dresses and make a salad.
Right.
Okay. So, all right. So it says like this. Okay. ולמאן דאמר
נמי התם בפה רך, Uleman de'amar nami hatam bepeh rach, even if
you say the first בפרך befarech was that they seduced them, הכא
ודאי בפריכה, Hacha vadai befrichah, now at this stage we're already up
to the crushing labor because it says וימררו את חייהם. Vayemareru et
hayeihem. דרש רבי עבירא, Darash Rabbi Avira, בשכר נשים צדקניות, Bisechar nashim
tzidkaniyot, for
the merit of the righteous women שהיו באותו הדור Shehayu be'oto hador
of that generation, נגאלו ישראל ממצרים, Nigalu Yisrael miMitzrayim, it was because
of them that we were ultimately redeemed. בשעה שהולכות לשאוב מים, Bishah
sheholchot lishoav mayim, when they went to draw water, הקדוש ברוך הוא
מזמין להם דגים קטנים בכדיהן, Hakadosh Baruch Hu mazmin lahem dagim ktanim
bekadeihen, so they got like little fish, I don't know, minnows or
sardines. Maybe that's the דגה? daga? Right, right, maybe that's the דגה.
daga. Anyway, little fish, herring, I don't know. No, herring is big,
it's just chopped up into small things. Sardines. Okay. ושואבות מחצה מים
ומחצה דגים, Veshoavot mechtzah mayim umechtzah dagim, and
their buckets came up half water and half fish.
ובאות ושופתות שתי קדירות, Uva'ot veshoftot shtei kdeirot, they would put on
the fire two pots, אחת של חמין Achat shel hamin אחת של
חמין ואחת של דגים achat shel chamin v'achat shel dagim one to
heat up the water and the other to cook the fish, ומוליכות
אצל בעליהן לשדה u'molichot etzel ba'aleihen lasadeh and they would bring it
out to their husbands in the field.
But the men were busy doing backbreaking work.
I don't know what to tell you. You can't make all the
מדרשים Midrashim work together. ומרחיצות u'marchitzot
so okay in that context I just have to tell you the
famous story joke whatever. Anyway because it's this week's פרשה, parsha, so
this week's פרשה parsha it says וה' ברך את אברהם בכל. v'Hashem
berach et Avraham bakol. So רש"י quotes the famous מדרש Midrash that
says בת היה לו ובכל שמה. bat hayah lo u'vakol shemah. He
had a daughter and her name was בכל Bakol from you know
his new wife or קטורה Keturah whoever it was.
So תוספות Tosafot there asks, he says I don't understand, so why
did he have to send the servant to go find a wife
for יצחק? Yitzchak? This was
יצחק's Yitzchak half-sister through a different mother, which is מותר mutar to
בני נח. Bnei Noach. So he should have just married יצחק Yitzchak
off to this his daughter. So you know what the answer is?
יצחק Yitzchak wanted to marry a real woman, not a מדרש. Midrash.
So anyway, bravo, there you
go.
Okay. So anyway so let's not try to make all the מדרשים
Midrashim work, okay, together.
Alright, anyway, ובאות ושופתו שתי קדירות, u'vaot v'shaftu shtei kdirot, אחת של
חמין ואחת של דגים, achat shel chamin v'achat shel dagim, okay, one
of water and one of fish, ומוליכות אצל בעליהן לשדה u'molichot etzel
ba'aleihen lasadeh and they brought it to their husbands in the field.
ומרחיצות אותן u'marchitzot otan and they would bathe their husbands, וסכות אותן
v'sakot otan and they would anoint them, I don't know where they
got the oil, maybe the fish oil, ומאכילות אותן u'machilot otan and
they would feed them, ומשקות אותן u'mashkot otan and have them drink.
So then you'd feel good, not only would you have strength but
you know your body is revived through that process. ונזקקות להן v'nizkakot
lahen and then they had the desire to have sex.
ונזקקות להן בין שפתים v'nizkakot lahen bein shfatayim and therefore and they
had sex with their
wives, right, so yes. So here clearly it's the opposite, it's the
righteous
women with the you know using sex and the sexual drive of
men or whatever to ultimately lead to the redemption. You know and
if you think about it, it's going back to the יהודה Yehuda
and תמר Tamar story also, right? Where again the woman was the
initiator and it was about sex and it was also about the
redemption, it was about ultimately leading to דוד המלך, David Hamelech, right?
So it's very interesting, exactly you know to sex leading to the
downfall when like you know the drive takes you outside of the
marriage and to do inappropriate things, or can it ultimately also like
bring about the redemption?
שנאמר, shenemar אם תשכבון בין שפתים, im tishkevun bein shfatayim, if you
lie down between the folds, בזכות תשכבון בין שפתים bizchut tishkevun bein
shfatayim and because of the merit of it that they lie down
between the folds,
זכו ישראל לביזת מצרים, zachu Yisrael l'vizat Mitzrayim, ultimately they merited the
you know the booty of Egypt. שנאמר, shenemar כנפי יונה נחפה בכסף,
kanfei yonah nechpah v'chesef, this is the end of the פסוק pasuk?
of אם תשכבון בין שפתים, im tishkevun bein shfatayim, that's how it
connects. Okay. The wings of a dove covered in silver ואברותיה בירקרק
חרוץ v'evroteha b'yerakrak charutz and again I think it's its limbs, its
wings in the like a filigree of gold. וכיון, v'keivan, so they
got all of that booty. וכיון שמתעברות v'keivan she'mitabrot and once they
became pregnant, ובאות לבתיהן u'vaot l'vateihen they would come to their homes.
וכיון שהגיע זמן מולדיהן v'keivan she'higia zman moldeihen and when it was
time for them to give birth, and the decree was out, right?
Because presumably the point is that husbands had to be seduced. Why
they be seduced? Number one is they had no sex drive, they
were exhausted, and number two, who wants to have children if there's
an edict out that they're just going to be thrown in the
river? So the wives had to seduce their husbands but here it
was a seduction that led to the גאולה. geulah. Okay. והולכות ויולדות
בשדה v'holchot v'yoldot basadeh and then they went there to go out
and give birth where nobody would see them give birth. Right. Out
in the field. תחת התפוח tachat hatapuach under the תפוח, tapuach, under
the apple trees. Yeah. The question is what's a תפוח? tapuach? We
defined it as apple but apparently apples were not are not indigenous
to the Middle East. So some people want to say that a
תפוח tapuach maybe an אתרוג etrog or some other type of a
fruit. I had a friend who once said to me, you know
it says, what's the פסוק? pasuk It says לא פסוק מדרש, lo
pasuk Midrash, מדרש Midrash says ריח בני
כריח שדה אשר ברכו ה', reiach bni k'reiach sadeh asher beracho Hashem,
so it says כריח שדה של תפוחים. k'reiach sadeh shel tapuchim. So
he said, did you ever smell an apple orchard? It does not
smell nice. So you know anyway, so that's very doubtful that תפוח
tapuach was what?
some other orchard. It's actually apple you understand originally by the way
just meant fruit, right? The apple of the eye, right? That's why
that's how come the the whole idea of the fruit of the
גן עדן, Gan Eden, right? That they ate from the tree, the
apple, right? Why did it become an apple? It's not indigenous to
the Middle East, but early translations had it as apple which had
a generic meaning of fruit. Think about how we say what's a
what do you call it, a potato? It's a תפוח אדמה. tapuach
adamah. Why isn't it an apple of the ground? Right? So anyway,
תפוח tapuach originally had an original apple originally had a generic meaning
of fruit. תחת התפוח עוררתיך, tachat hatapuach orarticha,
under the תפוח tapuach I have bestirred you. Okay.
So meaning is bestirred the kids to come
out?
I guess. I would have
thought that's where they would have sex. Oh, right, that's a good
point too. Anyway, והקב"ה שולח משמי מעון v'Hakadosh Baruch Hu sholeach mishmei
maon
Anyway,
that's yeah that's a different part of the story. Anyway, somebody who
would like clean and ready them up, you know, cleaned them up.
כחיה זו שמשפרת את הולד kechaya zu shemeshaperes es havelad like a
midwife who after the child is born, cleans it up and, you
know, and gives it good, you know, and washes it and so
on and and makes it healthy. שנאמר shenemar, ומולדותיך ביום הולדת אותך
umoladosayich beyom holedes osach thank you ביום הולדת אותך, beyom holedes osach,
לא כרת שרך lo kores sharach
and on the day that you were born, this is the end
of that פסוק pasuk from- oh no, this is the פסוק pasuk,
in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, different פסוק, pasuk excuse me. And the day that
you were born, לא כרת שרך, lo kores sharach, your flesh had
not been cut, meaning
your your umbilical cord, your navel. ובמים לא רחצת uvamayim lo ruchatzat
and you had not been bathed with
water למשעי. lemish'i. I don't know what למשעי lemish'i is. Anyway, ומלקט
להם. umelaket lahem. Anyway, so you had not been bathed and God
went ahead and sent for them something that would bathe them and
take care of them. ומלקט להם שני עגולים. umelaket lahem sheni agulim.
And whatever this thing was that God sent, gathered for them two
cakes, אחד של שמן ואחד של דבש, achad shel shemen ve'achad shel
devash, one of oil and one of honey. שנאמר- yeah, for bathing?
I don't
know, to give them honey. I know, I know. שנאמר ויניקהו דבש
מסלע ושמן מחלמיש צור. shenemar vayenikehu devash misela veshemen mechalmish tzur. Okay,
so God caused them to nurse, you know, honey from the rock.
Okay, so I think it's also ויניקהו, vayenikehu, it's the nursing. ושמן
מחלמיש צור.
veshemen mechalmish tzur.
Right, it's the nursing. וכיון שמכירין בהן מצריים, vekeivan shemakirin bahen mitzrayim,
once the Egyptians realized that something was happening and the children were
being born, so באו להורגן, bau lehorgan, they came to kill them,
the babies, okay. ונעשה להם נס, vena'asa lahem nes, and a miracle
was done. ונבלעין בקרקע, venivla'in bakarka, and they were swallowed up in
the ground out there by the apple or the תפוח tapuach orchard,
whatever. ומביאין שוורים, umevi'in shevarim, so then they figured, okay, they're buried
in the ground, we'll kill them there. So they brought oxen וחורשין
על גביהן, vechorshin al gabeihen, and they plowed over where the babies
were buried. שנאמר על גבי חרשו חרשים, shenemar al gabi charashu charashim,
on my back the plowers have plowed. But presumably they were too
far down and they were
protected. ואחר שהולכין, ve'achar sheholchin, after the Egyptians left, היו מבצבצין ויוצאין.
hayu mevatzbetzin veyotzin. Then the babies would resprout out of the ground
כעשב השדה, ke'esev hasadei, like the grass. שנאמר רבבה כצמח השדה נתתיך.
shenemar revava ketzemach hasadei nesatich. We all know this פסוק pasuk because
this is from the פסוק pasuk in the הגדה. Hagaddah. Okay, but
it was the end of that earlier פסוק pasuk about the day
that you were born, which was a whole metaphor about what do
you call it, a metaphor about the forming of the nation. That's
actually what that is there in יחזקאל. Yechezkel. That was, you know,
the meta- you were naked and and bloody and I cleaned you
and I made you a nation. So it's sort of the the
birthing of the nation. And here it's taking that metaphor and connecting
it to the birthing of the nation, but in the very literal
sense of the birthing of these children.
And that's where we're getting this ground stuff from. This would be
the פסוק pasuk they're quoting in the סידור Siddur there, because it's
והומלח לא המלחת. vehomleiach lo humalachta. So לא חתלת. lo chutilta.
Which means you weren't swaddled, so God swaddled them. Maybe. Okay. ותצמח
ותגדל ותבוא בעדי עדיים, vatitzmechi vatigdali vatavoi ba'adi adayim, and you you
grew up and you came בעדי עדיים, ba'adi adayim, like which is
in like jewelry. אל תקרי בעדי עדיים אלא בעדרי עדרים, al tikrei
ba'adi adayim ela be'edrei adarim, do not read jewelry,
but in flocks. Okay. Oh, I'm sorry, did I skip a line?
I skipped a line. רבבה כצמח השדה נתתיך. revava ketzemach hasadei nesatich.
וכיון שמתגדלים, vekeivan shemisgadlim, once they would then grow up, באין עדרים
עדרים לבתיהם. ba'in adarim adarim levateihem. So they they would come, they
would come flocks to their house, which by the way, it's like
very much like this thing of like being born in nature, you
know, not exactly raised by the wolves, but there they are, they
come up from the ground and they come home like flocks, like
flocks of sheep, right? So they're almost like, you know, these naturally
born animals that are now coming in from the field. It's an
interesting image. And we're going to see the animal theme come up
later. They would come flocks to the house. שנאמר, it says, ותצמח
ותגדל ותבוא בעדי עדיים. vatitzmechi vatigdali vatavoi ba'adi adayim. אל תקרי בעדי
עדיים אלא בעדרי עדרים. al tikrei ba'adi adayim ela be'edrei adarim. Do
not read in jewelry, but in flocks. וכשנגלה הקדוש ברוך הוא על
הים, ucheshenigla HaKadosh Baruch Hu al hayam, and when God revealed himself
on the sea, הם הכירוהו תחילה. hem hikiruhu techila. They were the
first to recognize God because they recognized God out there in the
field when they were infants, that God took care of them and
bathed them and whatever it was, that was through God that that-
and so they had already known God from that. שנאמר זה אלי
ואנוהו. shenemar zeh keili ve'anveihu. They were able to point to God,
"I know this, that's my God!" They recognized God. Okay. ויאמר מלך
מצרים למילדות העבריות. vayomer melech mitzrayim lamyaldot ha'ivriyot. So he said to
the Hebrew nursemaids. By the way, there's an interesting מחלוקת המפרשים machlokes
hamefarshim whether עבריות ivriyot means that the nursemaids were Hebrew or were
they nursemaids for the Hebrews. Some want to say that they were
Egyptian nursemaids. That's certainly not what the גמרא says. Okay. רב ושמואל.
Rav uShmuel. חד אמר אשה ובתה, chad amar isha uvita, one says
a mother and her daughter. וחד אמר כלה וחמותה, vechad amar kala
vachamosa, no, a daughter-in-law and her mother-in-law. מאן דאמר אשה ובתה יוכבד
ומרים, man de'amar isha uvita Yocheved uMiriam, it was Yocheved and Miriam.
That's what everybody knows like that מדרש. midrash. מאן דאמר כלה וחמותה
יוכבד ואלישבע. man de'amar kala vachamosa Yocheved ve'Elisheva. It was Elisheva, it
was Aaron's wife, her daughter-in-law. תניא כמאן דאמר אשה ובתה. tanya keman
de'amar isha uvita. דתניא שפרה זו יוכבד. detanya Shifra zu Yocheved. שפרה
Shifra was יוכבד. Yocheved. ולמה נקרא שמה שפרה שממשפרת את הולד, velama
nikra shema Shifra shemeshaperes es havelad, that she makes the child- is
like a good, like you know, improves him, but improves him, you
know, like takes, whatever, treats him, שפרה Shiphrah when he's just born.
שפרה שפרו ורבו ישראל בימיה, Shiphrah sheparu ve'ravu Yisrael beyameha, that they
increased, שפרו ורבו, sheparu ve'ravu, were fruitful and multiplied because then she
was obviously instrumental in that. פועה, Puah, and what's פועה? Puah? זו
מרים. zu Miryam. ולמה נקרא שמה פועה? velama nikra shemah Puah? שהייתה
פועה, she'hayta po'ah, that she would like like a coo in order
to help the child come out. דבר אחר, davar acher, שהייתה פועה
ברוח הקודש, she'hayta po'ah beruach hakodesh, she would speak with the divine
spirit ואומר עתיד אמי שתלד בן שמושיע את ישראל, ve'omer atid immi
she'teled ben shemoshiya et Yisrael, ultimately my mother will give birth to
a son who will be the savior of Israel. That's right, מושיען
של ישראל, moshi'an shel Yisrael, therefore you're right, probably it does mean
Moshe and not God. Anyway, I just got to read you this
little תוספות, Tosfos, שהייתה פועה לולד, she'hayta po'ah lavlad, תוספות Tosfos says,
פירוש בן חננאל, perush ben chananel, לא חשות לחישה, lo chashot lichisha,
an incantation, ויוצא הולד, ve'yotze havlad, to help the child be born,
כמו שעושים אלו עכשיו באזני האשה, k'mo she'osim elu achshav be'oznei ha'ishah,
like they do now, they whisper incantations to a woman who's giving
birth to help her give birth. Okay. ויאמר בילדכן את העבריות, Vayomer
beyaledchen et ha'ivriyot, when you give birth to the Hebrews, מאי אבנים,
mai avnayim, what is this word stones, the birthing stone? אמר רבי
חנן סימן גדול מסר להן. amar Rabbi Chanan siman gadol masar lahen.
He gave them a way to know that they were about to
give birth. אמר להם בשעה שכרעה ללדת, amar lahem besha'ah shekar'ah laledet,
when a woman is crouching to give birth, ירכותיה מצטננות כאבנים, yarchoteiha
mitztanenot ka'avanayim, and her thighs are cold like stone, and then you'll
know she's about to give birth and that will be when you
have to like be there to make sure she doesn't hide the
child and that you can kill the child. ואיכא דאמרי, v'ika d'amri,
and some say, כדכתיב וארד בית היוצר והנה הוא עשה מלאכה על
האבנים, kidichtiv va'ered beit hayotzer v'hinei hu oseh melachah al ha'avnayim, I
went to the potter's
house and he was doing work by the potter stone. מאי יוצר
זה, mai yotzer zeh, the same way a potter, ירך מכאן וירך
מכאן וסדן באמצע, yerech mikan v'yerech mikan v'sadan ba'emtza, he puts one
side here and the other side there and the potter platform, the
potter stone in the middle, אף אשה ירך מכאן וירך מכאן והולד
באמצע, af ishah yerech mikan v'yerech mikan ve'havlad ba'emtza, and a woman's
giving birth, one side is there, one side is there, her thighs
are spread and the child comes out in the middle. Okay, that's
why it's called a birthing stone, I guess similar metaphor. Okay. אם
בן הוא והמתן אתו, im ben hu vahamiten oto, if he's a
boy you should kill him. אמר רבי חנינא סימן גדול מסר להן.
amar Rabbi Chanina siman gadol masar lahen. Here's how you'll know immediately,
even before like checking, you'll know immediately if he's a boy or
a girl. בן פניו למטה, ben panav lematah, if he's a son
he'll come out face down, בת פניה למעלה, bat paneha lemalah, a
girl face up. Why? Because that ties into the Gemara's understanding that
children are born based on how they were conceived. And since the
Gemara's assuming that the man is above and the woman is below
when they're having sex, so they're also going to be not only
conceived based on how they're born but born the way the positions
of the parents were when they were conceived.
Okay.
So the child, if it's a boy it'll follow the position of
the man and if it's a girl it'll follow the position of
the mother. Okay. ותיראן המילדת את האלקים, vatirena ha'meyaldot et ha'Elokim, they
feared God, ולא עשו כאשר דבר אליהן מלך מצרים. velo asu ka'asher
diber aleihen melech mitzrayim. להן מיבעי ליה. lahen mibaei lei. It should
be להן lahen to them but I mean it's funny, דבר להן
daber lahen to them is more appropriate than אליהן aleihen which is
a little more like at them or something. So what's the אליהן?
aleihen? אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא מלמד שתבען לדבר עבירה. amar Rabbi
Yose bar Chanina melamed she'tev'an lidvar aveirah. He tried to seduce them
to sex, because Rashi
says it's like לבוא אליה lavo eleiha to go into her is
sometimes used as the word for sex. What? Pharaoh tried to seduce
the ילדות yeladot to have sex with him. ולא נתבעו, v'lo nit'bu,
so they refused him on that account as well. We'll read one
more, one more line. ותחיינה את הילדים, v'tichayena et hayeladim, and gave
life to the children. תנא לא דיין שלא המיתו אלא שהיו מספיקות
להן מים ומזון, tana lo dayan shelo hemitu ela shehayu maspikot lahen
mayim u'mazon, they didn't kill the kids but they gave life to
them,
they gave them bread and
sustenance. כי לא כנשים המצריות העבריות כי חיות הנה. ki lo k'nashim
hamitzriot ha'ivriyot ki chayot hen. I just wanted to end with this
חיות chayot
because it ties back to the חיה chaya metaphor before. Because they
are חיות. chayot. So what does חיות chayot mean? אילימא חיות ממש,
eili'ma chayot mamash, it's funny, Gemara thinks חיות ממש chayot mamash means
midwife, because חיה chaya for the Gemara's a midwife. If it means
they're midwives and therefore they can do it themselves, they don't need
a midwife, they're not going to call us, they're their own midwife.
אטו חיה מי לא צריכה חיה אחריתי? atu chaya mi lo tzaricha
chaya achrita? I don't understand, a midwife when she's giving birth needs
a midwife. A barber needs a barber to cut his hair. לולדיי,
le'vludei, to give birth. אלא אמרו לו אומה זו כחיה נמשלה. ela
amru lo uma zu k'chaya nimshala. No, it means that they're beasts,
they're animals. They give birth without help like animals of the field.
And this is like they're like animals: יהודה גור אריה יהודה, Yehudah
gur aryeh Yehudah, דן יהי דן נחש, Dan yehi Dan nachash, נפתלי
אילה שלחה, Naftali ayalah shlucha, יששכר חמור גרם, Yissachar chamor garem, all
of this connection to animals; יוסף בכור שור, Yosef bechor shor, בנימין
זאב יטרף, Binyamin ze'ev yitrof, דכתיב ביה ודלא כתיב ביה, d'chtiv bei
u'dlo chtiv bei, those that are connected to animals it's written, ודלא
כתיב ביה כתיב, ud'lo chtiv bei ktiv, and if it's not written
it's written מה אמך לביא בין אריות, mai imcha laviya bein arayot,
your mother was a lioness, your mother is a lioness, so they
were all born, we're all animals. So therefore,
so we'll end with this, so they basically they're animals, they don't
need our help. So I think that a very nice by the
way פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, I don't even think that
this is דרוש, drash, first of all it connects back to the
image that there they are, they're being born in the field and
they're coming back as flocks, which picks that up. But there's also
a nice point to be made about how the fact that, you
know, part of the process of enslaving a people, you know, is
the process and, you know. Think about of recently in terms of
the Holocaust of of is dehumanizing them and that the way in
which they're being dehumanized right so it says you know hey what
is it המה בני ישראל hemah b'nei Yisrael what is it ויקם
vayakom there's a פסוק pasuk and I can't I'm forgetting anyway
whatever it is part of the process was if you look at
the early פסוקים psukim when it speaks about that they are רב
ועצום ממנו rav v'atzum mimenu what is it הבה נתחכמה לו hava
nitchakma lo oh I can't think of it
anyway whatever it is anyway part of as it seems that the
point was that there's an earlier פסוק pasuk that reflects this idea
that they were sort of being seen by the מצריים Mitzrim as
animals and being dehumanized and it seems that that's what the when
they say back they're animals they give birth without חיות chayot that
פרעה Paroh was able to buy that lie because he already had
begun like a process of dehumanizing so that was actually able but
I'm not remembering hold on let me just give me one more
second I just can't it's frustrating here and we're a little over
but I just need to read you this פסוק it says one
minute
here
שמות Shemot
yeah hold on here it
is says alright alright I'm not finding it everybody's gathered up okay
it's okay it's okay it's alright we'll save the דרשה some other
time it's alright I can't find it okay to be continued fine
yes just something
someone shared with me how the experience of being dehumanized in the
camps yeah.